Guide to the John McDonald Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Other Papers, 1911-1998; Series III; 8.58; (9 boxes)
  Organized into five subseries: American Committee for the Defense of Leon Trotsky; American Film Center; Logs/Notebooks/Daily Notes; Subject Files; and Books, Pamphlets, and Serials.
  The series contains papers related to McDonald's personal projects and employment prior to his career at Fortune magazine, and reference material related to his interests; it includes his files on the Moscow Trials and the American Film Center, his Logs/Notebooks/Daily Notes, and a collection of printed Books, Pamphlets, and Serials related to his work in business, fishing, politics, and labor history. The subseries American Committee for the Defense of Leon Trotsky documents McDonald's involvement with the Dewey Commission and other radical activities. It contains John McDonald and Dorothy Eisner's correspondence with Leon Trotsky, which includes three letters from Trotsky. The American Film Center subseries consists of his office correspondence and two bound sets of Film News, the serial he edited. The Logs/Notebooks/Daily Notes subseries contains a run of chronologically organized spiral-bound notebooks and other loose sheets of paper dated between 1979 and 1997, which functioned for McDonald somewhat like commonplace books: he made lists of tasks to be done, wrote down random thoughts, and occasionally made almost diary-like descriptions of his daily activities; a single folder holding similar material from the mid-1950s was also filed here. Subject Files contains random clippings and notes on topics and people of interest to McDonald, in both his personal and professional lives.
  The last subseries holds copies of printed works used by McDonald for research or personal interest; most are also available in other Yale University Library collections, although many of the copies here were annotated by McDonald. Any academic papers and offprints on business topics were left the Series II research files with correspondence from the authors. The literature filed here covers business, fishing, labor and politics, and Detroit history. In addition to the titles listed, the political literature contains copies of pamphlets and serials published by the Workers Party of the United States and other socialist and communist organizations. The final section, Other Literature, holds copies of three state guides prepared under the Federal Writers' Project of the Work Projects Administration, where he served briefly as an editor.
  - American Committee for the Defense of Leon Trotsky (Dewey Commission)
    - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 37, Folder 1173)
    - Mission to Moscow, book and film, 1942-1943 (Box 37, Folder 1174)
    - Solow, Herbert, newspaper articles from The Sun, 1938 (Box 37, Folder 1175)
    - Trotsky, Leon, 1937-1938 (Box 37, Folder 1176)
      Includes letter to Trotsky signed by Albert Goldman and Herbert Solow
    - Miscellaneous, 1937-1939 (Box 37, Folder 1177)
      Includes photographs of Solow, Trotsky, Dewey, and commissioners, in Mexico; see the Dorothy Eisner Papers for additional photographs and correspondence
  - American Film Center
    - Correspondence, 1941-1945, 1957 (Box 37, Folder 1178-1179)
    - Film treatments, 1939-1945 (Box 37, Folder 1180)
    - Miscellaneous notes, 1940-1945, undated (Box 37, Folder 1181)
    - Film News (bound volume), 1940-1941 (Box 37, Folder 1182)
    - Film News (bound volume), 1940-1945 (Box 37, Folder 1183)
    - Folder number not used (Box 37)
  - Logs/Notebooks/Daily Notes
    - Notes, 1954-1955 (Box 38, Folder 1185)
    - Notes, 1979-1987 (Box 38, Folder 1186-1210)
    - Notes, 1988-1997 (Box 39, Folder 1211-1233)
    - Notes, random, undated (Box 40, Folder 1234-1246)
  - Subject Files
    - Angling, 1947-1992, undated (Box 40, Folder 1247-1248)
    - Bell curve, 1994 (Box 40, Folder 1249)
    - Brookner, Anita, 1996-1997, undated (Box 40, Folder 1250)
    - Croquet, 1978-1992 (Box 40, Folder 1251)
    - Dancing, 1990-1992 (Box 40, Folder 1252)
    - Derrida, Jacques, 1986, undated (Box 40, Folder 1253)
    - Gambling, 1949-1952 (Box 40, Folder 1254)
    - Game theory history conference, Duke University, 1990 (Box 40, Folder 1255)
    - Game theory, miscellaneous, 1994 (Box 40, Folder 1256)
    - Hook, Sidney, 1982, 1984 (Box 40, Folder 1257)
    - Horse racing, 1947-1996 (Box 40, Folder 1258-1261)
    - Joyce, James, 1991 (Box 40, Folder 1262)
    - Keene, J. Harrington, undated (Box 40, Folder 1263)
    - Keinbusch, William, 1980, undated (Box 40, Folder 1264)
    - Montana, 1953-1988, undated (Box 40, Folder 1265-1267)
    - Nova Scotia, 1988 (Box 40, Folder 1268)
    - Obituaries. miscellaneous, 1954-1997 (Box 41, Folder 1269)
    - Parker, Sanford S., 1980 (Box 41, Folder 1270)
    - Pessimism, 1955 Nov 1 (Box 41, Folder 1271)
    - Russian history, 1980-1996 (Box 41, Folder 1272)
    - Socialists, etc., 1977-1987
    - Trilling, Lionel and Diana, 1955-1997 (Box 41, Folder 1273)
    - Vance, Eugene, 1966-1967, undated (Box 41, Folder 1274)
    - Miscellaneous clippings, newspaper tear sheets, and book review issues, 1944-1998 (Box 41, Folder 1275-1285)
  - Books, Pamphlets, and Serials
    Arranged under the headings of Business Literature, Fishing Literature, Labor History/Political Literature, and Other Literature
    - Business literature
      - Biblical Games: a strategic analysis of stories in the Old Testament, by Steven J. Brams, 1980 (Box 42, Folder 1286)
      - "Contributions to Administration by Alfred P. Sloan, Jr., and GM," by Ernest Dale, in Administrative Science Quarterly, 1956 (Box 42, Folder 1287)
      - Contributions to the Theory of Games, vol. 4, edited by H.W. Kuhn and A.W. Tucker, 1959 (Box 42, Folder 1288)
      - Design for Decision, by Irwin D.J. Bross, 1953 (Box 42, Folder 1289)
      - Fights, Games, and Debates, by Anatol Rapoport, 1960 (Box 42, Folder 1290)
      - Game Theory: a nontechnical introduction, by Morton D. Davis, 1970 (Box 42, Folder 1291)
      - Game Theory and Related Approaches to Social Behavior, edited by Martin Shubik, 1964 (Box 42, Folder 1292)
      - Game Theory in the Behavioral Sciences, edited by Ira R. Buchler and Hugo G. Nutini, 1969 (Box 42, Folder 1293)
      - Games and Decisions, by R. Duncan Luce and Howard Raiffa, 1957 (Box 42, Folder 1294)
      - Harvard Business Review, 1954 Mar-Apr (Box 42, Folder 1295)
      - N-person Game Theory, by Anatol Rapoport, 1970 (Box 42, Folder 1296)
      - Pierre S. Du Pont and the Making of the Modern Corporation, by Alfred D. Chandler Jr. and Stephen Salsbury, 1971 (Box 42, Folder 1297)
      - Prisoner's Dilemma, by Anatol Rapoport and Albert M. Chammah, 1965 (Box 42, Folder 1298)
      - Recent Advances in Game Theory: papers delivered at a meeting of the Princeton University Conference, October 4-6, 1961, 1962 (Box 42, Folder 1299)
      - The Strategy of Conflict, by Thomas C. Schelling, 1960 (Box 43, Folder 1300)
      - Theory of Games and Economic Behavior, by John Von Neumann, and Oskar Morgenstern, 2nd ed., 1947 (Box 43, Folder 1301)
      - Theory of Games and Economic Behavior, by John Von Neumann, and Oskar Morgenstern, 3rd ed., 1953 (Box 43, Folder 1302)
      - Two-Person Game Theory: the essential ideas, by Anatol Rapoport, 1966 (Box 43, Folder 1303)
    - Fishing literature, 1940-1987 (Box 43, Folder 1304-1306)
    - Labor history/political literature
      - American Capitalism, the Concept of Countervailing Power, by John Kenneth Galbraith, 1952 (Box 43, Folder 1307)
      - American City; a rank-and-file history, by Charles Rumford Walker, 1937 (Box 43, Folder 1308)
      - American Labor Dynamics in the Light of Post-war Developments; an inquiry by thirty-two labor men, teachers, editors, and technicians, edited by J. B. S. Hardman, 1928 (Box 43, Folder 1309)
      - The Bullitt Mission to Russia; testimony before the Committee on Foreign Relations, United States Senate, of William C. Bullitt, 1919 (Box 43, Folder 1310)
      - Fascism & Big Business, by Daniel Guerin, 1939 (Box 43, Folder 1311)
      - History of the Commune of 1871, by Lissagaray, 1898 (Box 43, Folder 1312)
      - I Remember Detroit, by John C. Lodge, 1949 (Box 44, Folder 1313)
      - The Labor Movement in the United States, 1860-1895: a study in democracy, by Norman J. Ware, 1929 (Box 44, Folder 1314)
      - Russia and Germany at Brest-Litovsk: a documentary history of the peace negotiations, by Judah L. Magnes, 1919 (Box 44, Folder 1315)
      - The Story of Detroit, by George B. Catlin, 1926 (Box 44, Folder 1316)
      - The 20th Century Capitalist Revolution, by Adolf A. Berle Jr., 1954 (Box 44, Folder 1317)
      - Miscellaneous pamphlets and serials, 1911-1938 (Box 44, Folder 1318-1342)
      - Miscellaneous pamphlets and serials, 1934-1936 (Box 45, Folder 1343-1348)
      - Daily Worker, March 20, 1934 (photostat copies of two pages), undated
        Contains an article that mentions McDonald
    - Other literature
      - The Buildings of Detroit: a history (rev. ed.), by W. Hawkins Ferry, 1980 (Box 45, Folder 1349)
      - Canada, by Brian Moore and the editors of Life, 1967 (Box 45, Folder 1350)
      - Florida: a Guide to the Southern-most State, compiled and written by the Federal Writers' Project of the Work Projects Administration for the State of Florida, 1946 (Box 45, Folder 1351)
      - Garden Gateway to Canada: one hundred years of Windsor and Essex County, 1854-1954, by Neil F. Morrison (Box 45, Folder 1352)
      - History of Perth County to 1967, by W. Stafford Johnston and Hugh J. M. Johnston (Box 45, Folder 1353)
      - Michigan: a Guide to the Wolverine State, compiled and written by the Federal Writers' Project of the Work Projects Administration for the State of Michigan, 1956 (Box 45, Folder 1354)
      - Montana: a State Guide Book, compiled and written by the Federal Writers' Project of the Work Projects Administration for the State of Montana, 1939
- Oversize, 1.75; (9 boxes)
  - General correspondence, chronological files (in Series I), 1988 (Box 46, Folder 1355)
  - Calendars (wall) (in Series I), 1978-1988 (Box 46, Folder 1356)
  - Profile by Carl Little, in the Bar Harbor Times (in Series I), 1996 (Box 46, Folder 1357)
  - "Atlantic Salmon" and "The Leaper," in Fortune, June 1948 (in Series II), 1948 May 24 (Box 46, Folder 1358)
  - "Some Candid Answers from James J. Ling," in Fortune, August and September 1969 (in Series II), 1969-1970 (Box 47, Folder 1359-1361)
  - Fortune lists, notes, loose covers (in Series II), 1946-1971, undated (Box 48, Folder 1362-1366)
  - Fortune tear sheets and issues (in Series II), 1945-1947 (Box 48, Folder 1367-1377)
  - Fortune tear sheets and issues (in Series II), 1948-1950 (Box 49, Folder 1378-1388)
  - Fortune tear sheets and issues (in Series II), 1951-1969 (Box 50, Folder 1389-1407)
  - Rod & Reel, "Dan Bailey: 1904-1982," May/June 1982 (in Series II), 1981-1982 (Box 51, Folder 1408)
  - Town and Country, "A Trout Secret," May 1939 (in Series II) (Box 51, Folder 1409)
  - Letters to the Fishing Gazette (1891-1915) and Forest and Stream (1908-1915), photostats (in Series II), undated (Box 51, Folder 1410)
  - The Complete Fly Fisherman, dust jacket (in Series II), 1947 (Box 51, Folder 1411)
  - A Ghost's Memoir, newspaper clippings (in Series II), 1973-1992 (Box 51, Folder 1412)
  - My Years with General Motors, newspaper clippings (in Series II), 1952-1964 (Box 51, Folder 1413)
  - My Years with General Motors, "spoof" newspaper (in Series II), 1959 (Box 51, Folder 1414)
  - Berners' Treatise of Fishing with an Angle ([1515?]) (in Series II), 1957, undated (Box 52, Folder 1415-1416)
  - Berners' Treatise of Fishing with an Angle (1803) (in Series II), undated (Box 52, Folder 1417)
  - Berners' Treatise of Fishing with an Angle (1881) (in Series II), undated (Box 52, Folder 1418)
  - Berners' Treatise of Fishing with an Angle (1885) (in Series II), undated (Box 52, Folder 1419)
  - Biographia Britannica (1748) (in Series II), undated (Box 52, Folder 1420)
  - Chauncey's Historical Antiquaries (1700) (in Series II), undated (Box 52, Folder 1421)
  - Denison's Literal Translation (1872) (in Series II), undated (Box 52, Folder 1422)
  - DeWorde's editions of St. Albans (in Series II), undated (Box 52, Folder 1423)
  - Edward, "Master of the Game" (1406?) (in Series II), undated (Box 52, Folder 1424)
  - Holinshed's Chronicles (1577) (in Series II), undated (Box 52, Folder 1425)
  - Jacob on the Book of St. Albans (1944) (in Series II), undated (Box 52, Folder 1426)
  - Leland's Index (in Series II), undated (Box 52, Folder 1427)
  - Letters from Satchell to Denison (1883) (in Series II), undated (Box 52, Folder 1428)
  - Smith's introduction to Leland's Itinerary (1906) (in Series II), undated (Box 52, Folder 1429)
  - Miscellaneous texts from journals, by Haskins and others (in Series II), undated (Box 52, Folder 1430)
  - Cotton, Charles (1676) (in Series II), undated (Box 52, Folder 1431)
  - "Detroit" project: maps (in Series II), 1989-1980 (Box 53, Folder 1432)
  - "Detroit" project: McDonald drugstore photographs (in Series II), circa 1910 (Box 53, Folder 1433)
  - Subject files: Angling (in Series III), 1947, undated (Box 53, Folder 1434)
  - Subject files: Montana (in Series III), 1953-1988, undated (Box 53, Folder 1435-1436)
  - Subject files: Russian history (in Series III), 1980-1996 (Box 53, Folder 1437)
  - Subject files: Socialists, etc. (in Series III), 1977-1987 (Box 53, Folder 1438)
  - Subject files: miscellaneous clippings, newspaper tear sheets, and book review issues (in Series III), 1988-1989 (Box 53, Folder 1439)
  - Mission to Moscow, book and film (in Series III), 1942-1943 (Box 54, Folder 1440)
  - Labor history/political literature: issues of The Militant, March 10 and 17 (in Series III), 1934 (Box 54, Folder 1441)
  - Daily Worker, March 20, 1934 (photostat copies) (in Series III), undated (Box 54, Folder 1442)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.2; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted Fragile in box 55 may be consulted only with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies or photographic prints for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
  - Box 4, folder 110 (Box 55, Folder 1443)
  - Box 4, folder 111 (Box 55, Folder 1444)
  - Box 37, folder 1177 (Box 55, Folder 1445)